Okay, well this is it.
好的，事情就到此为止。
The end of the journey, the final class.
旅程的终点，最终的课堂。
So we've done a lot this year, right?
今年我们做了不少事，对吧？
Last semester we did the great books, the Iliad,
上学期我们读了伟大的书，伊利亚特，
the Odyssey, the Bible,
奥德赛，圣经，
Republic, Divine Comedy.
共和国，神曲。
This semester we did how screwed up the world is, right?
本学期我们讨论了世界到底有多乱，对吧？
The world is hopeless. We're all going to die.
世界一片混乱。我们都要死了。
And in this final class,
在这最后一堂课里，
I want this class to be about hope.
我想让这堂课充满希望。
And I want to show you the future.
我想给你们展示未来。
And the argument I want to leave you with,
我想留给你们的论点是，
the thing that I want you to remember is that,
我想让你记住的事是，
remember Dante in Divine Comedy said that
记得但丁在《神曲》中说过，
the future, the future is the future.
未来，未来就是未来。
And the future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is the future. And the future is not what happens to you.
未来就是未来。未来就是未来。未来就是未来。未来就是未来。未来就是未来。未来不是你所经历的事。
It's not something that you wait for.
它不是你等待的东西。
The future is what you imagine
未来是你想象的事。
and fight for.
并为之而战。
The future is what you make happen.
未来是你创造的。
There is a God, but
有一位神，
God gave us the ability to imagine
上帝赐给我们想象的能力
and the capacity to love.
以及爱的能力。
And it's these two things that will guide us
这两件事将指引我们。
and enable us to build a better world.
并使我们能构建更好的世界。
Okay? So that's the message I want to give to you today.
好的？这就是我今天想给你们的消息。
The future is what we imagine.
未来是我们想象的结果。
Not what we have to put up with.
不是我们必须忍受的事物。
So if we don't like the future, if we don't like the way we live our lives,
如果我们不喜欢未来，如果我们不喜欢我们生活的方式，
then we can change that with our imagination.
那么我们可以用想象去改变它。
And today I want to show you how.
今天我想给你们演示如何做。
So just to summarize what we did this semester.
简而言之，我们本学期做了什么。
Together we analyzed the world.
我们一起分析了世界。
But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
那还有另外两件你可以了解未来的事物是什么呢？
But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future. But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
那还有另外两件你可以了解未来的事物是什么呢？
But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future. But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
那还有另外两件你可以了解未来的事物是什么呢？那还有另外两件你可以了解未来的事物是什么呢？
But what are some of the other two things you can learn about the future.
那还有另外两件你可以了解未来的事物是什么呢？
millions and billions of people.
数以百万计的人。
And because of climate change,
因为气候变化，
our world will eventually collapse at some point, okay?
我们的世界最终会在某个时点崩溃，好的？
So this is an extremely hopeless,
于是这是一幅极其无望的，极其黯淡而黑暗的世界图景。
extremely bleak and dark picture of the world.
但记住，黑暗之处亦有光明。
But remember, where there is darkness, there can also be light.
So in this final class, I want to show you
于是在这最后一课，我想给你们展示一些希望和光明，好的？
some hope and some light, okay?
于是这就是我们所说的心理历史。
So this is what we call psychohistory.
So this is what wecall psychohistory.
And psychohistory is the idea
而心理历史就是这样一个想法
that the future can be predicted.
未来可以被预测。
And if it can be predicted, then it can be controlled
如果能预测，未来就能被掌控。
and harnessed for the betterment of humanity, okay?
并为人类的更好而被利用，好吗？
So where does this idea come from, psychohistory?
那么这个想法从哪里来，心理历史？
In the 1950s,
在1950年代，
there was an American science fiction writer named Isaac Asimov.
有一位美国科幻作家叫艾萨克·阿西莫夫。
And he's probably
他大概是……
the most famous science fiction writer, okay?
他是最著名的科幻作家，好吗？
If you happen to read science fiction, he's really famous.
如果你碰巧读过科幻，他真是大名鼎鼎。
And he wrote a series called Foundation.
他写了一系列叫《基地》的书。
And I think there's a TV series now based on Foundation books.
我觉得现在有一部基于《基地》书的电视剧。
It's terrible, but you can have a look at it.
太糟了，但你可以看看。
And in the Foundation books, he introduces the idea of psychohistory.
在《基地》书里，他提出了心理史的概念。
And so this book is set in the future,
于是这本书的背景设在未来。
like a million years from now, where there is a galactic empire.
大约一百万年后，出现了一个银河帝国。
So humanity has colonized the entire Milky Way.
于是人类已把整个银河系殖民化。
There are billions of planets.
星系中有数十亿颗行星。
And there's an empire that
还有一个帝国，把银河系带入和平。
brings peace to this Milky Way.
但所有帝国都必然崩溃。
But with all empires, it has to collapse.
And this will lead to 30,000 years of war,
于是会出现三万年的战争、暴力与野蛮。
violence, barbarity. But
但随后，基础提出了一门新科学——心理史学。
the foundation proposes a new science called psychohistory.
the foundation proposes a newscience called psychohistory.
Which is to mathematically map out
哪是把人类行为在一百万年间用数学映射出来。
human behavior over the course of a million years.
人类行为在一百万年间用数学映射出来。
But if you do that, what you discover is
that there are certain patterns to human society.
那表明人类社会存在某些模式。
But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain standards to human society. But the way you discover is that there are certain Okay?
但你发现的方式是人类社会存在某些标准。
And if that's the case, then you can predict the future.
如果是这样，你就能预测未来。
If you can do that, then
如果你能做到这一点，就能操纵事件进程，创造更好的未来。
you can manipulate the course of events to make a better future.
好的？这就是他所说的“心理历史”。
Okay? So this is what he called psychohistory.
And it's a science fiction concept.
它是科幻概念。
And a lot of people have been trying to make it into reality.
许多人已尝试把它变成现实。
Okay? So there's this very prominent historian.
于是出现了这位极具影响力的历史学家。
His name is Peter Turkin.
他的名字是彼得·图尔金。
And he's one of the founders of something called Clio Dynamics.
他是被称为克利奥动力学的某个组织的创始人之一。
Okay? And
好的？
Clio is the goddess of history.
克利奥是历史女神。
Dynamics just means movement.
动态只是指运动。
Okay? So
好的？
basically Clio Dynamics is trying to figure
基本上，克利奥动力学正试图弄清数学历史的运动规律。
out the mathematical movement of the mathematical history.
他正试图把历史建模成一个数学模型。
He's trying to create history as a mathematical model.
And when he did that, there's certain interesting trends
当他这么做时，出现了一些有趣的趋势
and patterns that he discovered.
以及他发现的模式。
Okay? And one idea that
好的吗？还有一个想法是。
he discovered is something called the
他发现的东西叫做
overproduction of
过度生产的
the elites.
精英
Okay? Overproduction of the elite.
好的？精英过度生产。
And this concept explains why.
这个概念解释了原因。
So this concept explains why societies collapse. Now, traditionally,
所以这个概念解释了社会崩溃的原因。
we've understood the collapse of societies as having to
我们已经把社会崩溃理解为可能与过多债务、过大不平等或气候变迁或战争有关。
do with maybe like too much debt or too much inequality or maybe climate change or war.
对吗？彼得·图尔金指出的，...
Right? What Peter Turkin points out, and
it's a really interesting idea,
这真是个很有趣的想法，
is the reason why societies collapse in the
是导致社会崩溃的原因，
end is you have too many elites.
最终是因为你有太多精英。
All right? So let me explain the concept.
好的！那我来解释一下这个概念。
Okay. So.
好的。那。
So.! Society has many elites.
于是！社会拥有许多精英。
Right? You have people like Jack Ma.
对吧？你有像马云那样的人。
Right? You have people like Zhou Xun, Zhao Wei.
对吧？你有像周迅、赵伟那样的人。
Right? Movie stars. You have famous military generals.
对吧？电影明星。你有著名的军队将领。
Okay? So
好的？那
over time, elites become more and more numerous.
随着时间推移，精英越来越多。
Right? The number of wealthy people go up.
对吧？富裕的人数增多。
The number of famous people go up.
名人数量增多。
The number of uneducated people go up.
未受教育者数量增多。
The number of entrepreneurs go up. Okay?
创业者数量增多。
The problem, though,
问题是，
is they all want power.
他们都想要权力。
Right? Now, wealth and
对吧？现在，财富和
fame are all infinite resources.
名气是所有无限资源。
Right? But
对吧？但
power will always be a finite resource.
权力永远是有限资源。
In fact, it's what we call a zero -sum game.
实际上，这就是我们所说的零和游戏。
So, for example, in this classroom, there can only be one teacher.
例如，在这个教室里，最多只能有一位老师。
Right? If we're all teachers, there's no teacher.
对吧？如果我们都是老师，那就没有老师。
So in society, there can only be a few powerful people.
于是，在社会中，最多只有少数强者。
If everyone has the power, no one has any power.
若人人皆有权力，便无一人有权力。
Okay? So what happens over time is that
好了？于是随着时间的推移，发生了……
all these people who
所有这些人都
believe they should have power struggle for power.
认为自己应该拥有权力，争夺权力。
And because there are too many of them,
而且因为他们太多，
this internal struggle of the elites ultimately leads to social collapse.
这场内部精英斗争最终导致社会崩溃。
Okay? So the most famous example is in China,
好啦？最著名的例子在中国，帝制中国。
in imperial China, where you have the Keju system.
在帝制中国，出现了科举制度。
Right? People taking the imperial examinations to become an official.
对吧？人们参加科举考试成为官员。
Problem is, you have too many candidates,
问题是，候选人太多，
not enough positions.
职位不够。
Right? And guess who ultimately gets upset with society
对吧？猜猜谁最终对社会不满并发动革命？是科举考生。
and leads revolutions? It's the Keju candidates.
谁没能当官。
Who do not become officials.
And so they become angry.
于是他们愤怒起来。
And they lead revolutions to overthrow society.
于是他们发动革命推翻社会。
Right? So
对吧？
the most classic example of the
最经典的例子是洪秀全。
failed Keju candidate is Hong Xiuquan.
洪秀全是个考生。
Do you guys know who he is?
你们知道他是谁吗？
The leader of the Taiping rebellion.
太平军的领袖。
Right? Why did he become a Christian?
对吧？他为什么会成为基督徒？
Why did he lead the rebellion?
他为什么发动太平军？
Because he failed the Keju.
因为他考取了科举。
Okay? So that's the idea of the overproduction of the elite.
好吧？这就是精英过度生产的概念。
And he discovered this principle using mathematically modeling of history.
他用历史的数学建模发现了这一原理。
He just compared different societies and
他只是比较了不同的社会并
tried to figure out why they collapsed.
尝试弄清它们为何崩溃。
Okay? And what he discovered is, well, it's because
好的？他发现的结果是，嗯，就是因为
of the internal struggle among the different elite groups.
不同精英团体内部斗争的结果。
Okay? And that's why the Roman Empire collapsed as well.
好吧？这也是罗马帝国崩溃的原因。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay.
好吧？这样说通吗？
What I'm proposing to you is that
我想给你提个建议
we can actually go a step further than what Peter Turchin is doing.
我们可以比彼得·图尔奇所做的更进一步
Because we have something called now called AI.
因为现在我们有了所谓的人工智能
Okay? Artificial intelligence. And
好吧？人工智能。和
we can harness the power of AI to create real psychohistory,
我们可以利用AI的力量来创造真正的心理历史，
which is the ability to not just analyze the past,
这就是不仅能分析过去的能力，
but to predict the future.
但用来预测未来。
Okay? All right.
好的。
So let's first figure out what AI is.
先来搞清楚AI是什么。
Okay? So first I want us to understand what artificial intelligence is.
好吧？先让我们弄清楚什么是人工智能。
Because most of you think you know, but you don't actually know.
因为你们大多数人觉得自己知道，但其实并不懂。
Okay? So what is AI?
好吧？那AI到底是什么？
All right. The AI, the technical term,
好的。AI，技术术语，是监督式机器学习。
is supervised
是监督式
machine learning.
机器学习。
Okay? That's the technical term.
好的？那是技术术语。
AI is the popular term, but
AI是大众术语，但
supervised machine learning is the technical
监督式机器学习是技术术语。
and correct term.
以及正确术语。
Have you guys heard of this term?
你们听说过这个术语吗？
Supervised machine learning.
监督式机器学习。
Yes or no? Have any of you taken computer science?
是或否？你们有人学过计算机科学吗？
Yes. Okay.
是。好的。
This is called supervised machine learning.
这叫做监督式机器学习。
Okay. So what is this?
好的。那么这是什么？
Okay. So in computer programming,
好的。在计算机编程里，
you're taught to write the algorithm, right?
你被教写算法，对吧？
And then the input. You put in information, it gives you the output.
然后是输入。你放入信息，它给你输出。
Okay? And this is traditionally how computers work.
好的？这就是传统的计算机工作方式。
You write the algorithm, the computer program,
你写算法，计算机程序。
you put in information, and then there's an output, right?
你放入信息，然后得到输出，对吧？
For example, the algorithm could be like, you know, A plus B.
比如，算法可以是这样，你知道，A 加 B。
Okay? So you put in two numbers. Two, two, you get a four.
好的？所以你放入两个数字，两个，得到四。
Okay? That's how computers work.
好的？这就是计算机的工作方式。
Right? Now, supervised machine learning is
对吧？现在，监督式机器学习是……
that I will turn the output into the input.
我会把输出变成输入。
Okay? And the reason why I want to do that
好的？我想这么做的原因是
is that as a human being,
作为人类，
I myself may not be able to write the best algorithm.
我自己可能写不出最优算法。
Okay? So
好的？那么
I want the computer to refine the algorithm for me,
我想让电脑为我完善算法，
to optimize it using the output.
用输出结果来优化它。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好的？这样说通吗？好吧。
So let's talk about a very specific example.
那我们来聊一个非常具体的例子。
All right? So
好吧？
let's look at facial recognition technology.
让我们来看看人脸识别技术。
All right? You go to the airport, and you scan,
好吧？你去机场，扫描一下，
and they know who you are.
然后他们就知道你是谁。
Right? You go to a supermarket, you scan your face, and you pay.
对吧？你去超市，扫描自己的脸，然后付款。
Right? And you're like, wait, how does that work?
对吧？你会想，等一下，这怎么做到的？
Okay. So
好的。
how this works is that there's a database,
这件事的工作原理是有一个数据库，
okay, about 1 billion people, like everyone in China.
好了，大约一亿人，像中国人一样。
And now what I need to do is figure out
现在我需要做的事是弄清楚。
how to differentiate the faces of everyone in China in this database.
如何在这个数据库里区分中国人所有人的面孔。
Okay? Does that make sense? So what I do is,
好？这有道理吗？于是我做的是，
for the face, I want to figure out how to differentiate the faces of everyone in China.
对面孔，我想弄清楚如何区分中国人所有人的面孔。
So I go to the database, I create a mathematical model based on topology.
于是我去数据库，基于拓扑创建了一个数学模型。
Okay? Does that make sense? Topology.
好？这有道理吗？拓扑。
So I turn everyone's face into a mathematical model.
于是我把每个人的面孔转化成数学模型。
Okay? Which looks like something like this.
好的？看起来像这样。
Okay? And you're like, I don't know what this is.
好的？你会说，我不知道这是什么。
Okay. You don't need to know what this is.
好的。你不需要知道这是什么。
This is like super complicated. Okay?
这就像超级复杂。好？
But all you need to know is that within this model,
但你只需要知道的是，在这个模型里，
there are different equations.
有不同的方程。
Okay? So for example,
好的？比如说，
this model is trying to analyze the distance between your eyes.
这个模型试图分析你眼睛之间的距离。
Okay? And how big your nose is.
好的？还有你鼻子的大小。
All right? Does that make sense? All right?
好的？那有道理吗？好的？
And so once I create this mathematical model,
于是我一旦创建了这个数学模型，
I am now able to differentiate everyone in
我就能把每个人区分出来。
China. Does that make sense? Okay?
中国。那有道理吗？好的？
In fact, this mathematical is so
事实上，这个数学模型非常精准，只有我能看见你的眼睛。
precise that I can only look at your eyes.
我现在可以只看你的眼睛。
And I know who you are. Okay? Because
我也知道你是谁。好的？因为
what I'm trying to do is match what your model with the model in the database.
我正在做的事是把你的模型与数据库里的模型匹配。
All right? But
好的？
what's important to remember is that if you're not in this database,
要记住的事是，如果你不在这个数据库里，就会被认不出来。
you can't be recognized.
好的？你明白了吗？
Okay? Do you understand? All right.
好啦。
Now, what I will show you is how this model is created.
现在，我要给你展示这个模型是如何创建的。
So what happens is this. All right?
于是发生的事就是这样。好吗？
What I do is I teach the computer how to create this database.
我做的是教电脑如何创建这个数据库。
So I have input. I have output. And then
于是我有输入，我有输出。然后
what I do is I create a
我做的是我创建一个
working thesis or a working theory of
工作论点或工作理论
what this model should look like. Okay?
这个模型应该是怎样的。好吗？
Does that make sense? All right?
这有道理吗？好吗？
So it could be like this. All right?
它可以是这样的。好吗？
And then what I do is I create a working thesis. So what I do is I put faces.
于是我做的是我创建一个工作论点。然后我把面孔放进去。
Okay? And the output should match what's in the database.
好了？输出应该与数据库里的内容匹配。
And if the model returns something that's different, I tell them this is wrong.
如果模型返回的结果不同，我就告诉它这是错误的。
And what the computer then does is refine this model until it becomes this.
于是电脑会把模型不断细化，直到它变成这样。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这有道理吗？好吗？
So what all AI is is infinite iteration.
所以所有AI就是无穷迭代。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好了？这有道理吗？好的。
All right. So
好的。那么
the problem with AI is I need
AI的问题是我需要
to be able to solve three things.
能够解决三件事。
And if I can solve three things, then I can create an AI.
如果我能解决三件事，那我就能造出一个AI。
Okay? The first thing is that
好了？第一件事是……
I need
我需要
clear metrics.
清晰的指标。
Okay? Or clear outputs.
好的？或者清晰的输出。
Okay? Does that make sense? I need outputs that
好的？那有道理吗？我需要的输出是……
I can define as a mathematical model.
我可以把它定义成一个数学模型。
Okay? So, for example,
好的？比如说，
if I'm an airline,
如果我是航空公司，
I'm going to use AI to maximize the amount of money I make on a flight.
我将使用人工智能来最大化每趟航班的收益。
Right? Okay? That's my output.
对吧？好的？这就是我的输出。
How much money can I make out of a flight?
一次航班能赚多少钱？
I want to have the maximum amount of profit.
我想获得最大的利润。
Okay? That's the first thing I need to solve.
好的？这就是我需要先解决的第一件事。
Second thing I need to solve then is to make sure that I have the right metrics.
第二件事我需要先解决的是确保我有正确的指标。
But the way I figured this out is, let's try and figure out what are the standards.
我想出来的办法是，先试着弄清楚标准是什么。
But let's try and figure out what are the standards.
再试着弄清楚标准是什么。
But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards.
再试着弄清楚标准是什么。再试着弄清楚标准是什么。
But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards. But let's try and figure out what are the standards.
再试着弄清楚标准是什么。再试着弄清楚标准是什么。再试着弄清楚标准是什么。再试着弄清楚标准是什么。再试着弄清楚标准是什么。
But let's try and figure out what are the standards.
再试着弄清楚标准是什么。
data sets of different animals.
不同动物的数据集。
Okay, does that make sense? I need to label my data.
好的，听得懂吗？我得给我的数据打标签。
But I can't tell,
但我说不出来，
I can't make an AI that's like, this is the best ice cream in the world.
我没法让AI说这就是世界上最好的冰淇淇。
And the reason why is, I can't find data
原因是，我找不到最佳冰淇淇的数据，你明白吗？
on the best ice cream, you understand?
因为冰淇淇，最佳冰淇淇是主观的。
Because ice cream, the best ice cream is subjective.
我无法把它变成数据集。
So I cannot turn that into a data set.
于是我就把它变成数据集。
Okay, does that make sense? Okay,
好的，听得懂吗？好的，
the third thing I need to
第三件事我需要
do is create a
做的是创建一个
working algorithm structure.
工作算法结构。
You understand, okay?
你明白，好的？
Computers can only refine and optimize
计算机只能细化并优化算法结构，自己却不能创造它。
the algorithm structure. It cannot create it by itself.
好的？如果我能完成这三件事，……
Okay? So if I'm able to do all three things,
then I'm able to do all three things.
然后我就能完成这三件事。
I can use AI to optimize
我可以用 AI 来优化
what I wanted to optimize.
我想要优化的东西。
Okay? All right, any questions so far?
好的？到目前为止，任何问题吗？
Before I move on? Okay?
在我继续之前？好的？
So what this means is that there are certain problems
所以这意味着有些问题是可以解决的
that I can solve using AI, and
我可以用 AI 解决的事，和
there are certain problems I cannot solve using AI, okay?
我可以用 AI 解决的事，还有我用 AI 解决不了的事，好的？
So what are easy problems?
那么什么是容易解决的问题？
What are some of the problems that AI can solve, right? Well, for example, facial recognition technology,
AI 能解决哪些问题？比如人脸识别技术，
okay? Also, translation software, right?
好的？还有翻译软件，对吧？
I can create an optimal translation software.
我可以开发出最优的翻译软件。
Also, recommendation engines, right?
还有推荐引擎，对吧？
So if you watch a movie on Netflix,
所以如果你在 Netflix 看电影，
it recommends another movie, right?
它会给你推荐另一部电影，对吧？
Okay? Now let me ask you this question.
好的？现在让我问你这个问题。
Can I ever solve,
我能解决自驾车吗？
self -driving cars? Can I ever solve self -driving cars?
Self -driving cars. Can cars drive by themselves?
自驾车。汽车能自己开吗？
Yes or no? Yes.
是或否？是。
Why yes, Sally?
为什么是，萨莉？
Because they're on.
因为它们在路上。
I mean, they're driving. Okay, the answer is no.
我的意思是它们在行驶。好的，答案是没有。
Why is the answer no? Okay, the answer no is,
为什么答案是没有？好的，答案是没有是，
whatever I do, okay, I cannot solve something called the edge case.
无论我做什么，好的，我无法解决所谓的边缘情况。
The edge case is, if the car is on the road,
边缘情况是，如果汽车在路上，
what could happen that would screw up my AI system?
会发生什么能把我的 AI 系统搞乱？
You guys know? Why can't self -driving cars be solved?
你们知道吗？为什么自动驾驶汽车还没搞定？
Why can't we have self -driving cars on the road?
为什么我们还没能让自动驾驶汽车上路？
What's an edge case?
什么是边缘情况？
Or this thing that I can never solve?
或者这件我永远解不出来的事？
What is it? Excuse me?
它是什么？请问一下？
Yeah, and what is not planned?
是的，什么没被计划？
Hm? They can plan for traffic.
嗯？他们能预先安排交通。
What can they not plan for?
他们还能预先安排什么？
And this is why we'll never have someone driving cars.
这就是我们永远不会有人开车的原因。
They can plan for accidents. What can they not plan for?
他们能预先安排事故。还有什么能预先安排？
Yeah? Easily plan for traffic rules.
嗯？很容易预先安排交通规则。
What can they not plan for? Okay, guys.
还有什么能预先安排？好了，大家。
The edge case with self -driving cars is if I,
边缘情况是自驾车，如果我，
as a human being, intentionally want to crash into that car.
作为人类，故意想撞上那辆车。
Do you understand? Does that make sense to you guys?
你们明白吗？这对你们来说有道理吗？
Every other situation I can plan for.
我能预先安排的其他情况都已列举。
But in a situation where I'm the human being,
但在我作为人类的情形里，
and I don't like self -driving cars because I'm a taxi driver,
我不喜欢自驾车，因为我是出租车司机。
and it's stealing my job, right?
它正在抢走我的工作，对吧？
It's stealing my livelihood, and I want to crash into that car.
它正在抢走我的生计，我想撞上那辆车。
There's no way for that
没有办法了。
AI to avoid the accident.
AI去避免事故。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这样说通吗？好吧？
Listen. Listen.
听着。听着。
AI is a scam, okay?
AI是个骗局，行吗？
It does not exist. What exists?
它不存在。存在的是？
What exists is supervised machine learning, okay?
存在的是监督式机器学习，行吗？
What is supervised machine learning? What I just told you, okay?
什么是监督式机器学习？我刚才说的，行吗？
That's it. That's the extent of our technology.
就是这样。就是我们的技术范围。
It does not have self -awareness.
它没有自我意识。
It can only do what the algorithm tells it to do.
它只能执行算法指令的动作。
And there's no way you can design an algorithm that
而且你无法设计出一个能预先规划并预防人类动作的算法。
plans for and prevents a human being
它计划并预防人类动作的算法也不存在。
who intentionally wants to crash into you.
谁故意撞上你。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
好？这样说通吗？没问题吗？
Okay? So AI, in other words,
好？所以AI，换句话说，
is actually a limited tool, okay?
它实际上是一个有限工具，明白吗？
So you think about actual applications of AI, it's very limited.
所以你在考虑AI的实际应用时，它很有限。
You also look at self -driving cars.
你还会看自驾车。
Now, there are cars that have self -driving features,
现在，有些车配备了自动驾驶功能，
but they are not 100% self -driving.
但它们并非百分百自动驾驶。
Okay? Does that make sense? In fact, they tell you,
好？这样说通吗？实际上，它们会告诉你…
don't rely on the autopilot, okay?
不靠自动驾驶，明白吗？
It's there to help you,
它是来帮你的，
but don't sleep in the car.
但别在车里睡觉。
Okay? Right? Because
好？对吗？因为
they don't have an AI system
它们没有 AI 系统
in place to prevent people from crashing into them.
来防止人们撞上它们。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好？这样说通吗？好。
So now that we know what AI is,
现在我们知道 AI 是什么了，
let's talk about how we can use AI
接下来聊聊我们如何使用 AI。
to predict the future.
预测未来。
Okay? Okay?
好？好？
All right. All right.
好。好。
So basically, what you need to do is three things,
所以基本上，你需要做三件事，
right? You need to be clear about the output,
对吧？你要把输出弄清楚，
you need to have clean data,
你要有干净的数据。
and you need to have a working algorithm.
并且你需要有一个可用的算法。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好？这样说通吗？
And so that's what I've been doing this semester.
于是这就是我本学期所做的工作。
Okay? So for example,
好的？比如说，
remember my predictions.
记住我的预测。
Okay? Okay?
好的？好的？
Okay? if you go to a legal lobby, Saudi Arabia
好的？如果你去法律游说，沙特阿拉伯
and the American Empire,
和美帝国
basically the need to protect the petrodollar,
基本上是要保护石油美元
will force America to go to war with Iran.
将迫使美国与伊朗开战。
Okay? These are the push factors.
好的吗？这些是推动因素。
The problem is that
问题在于…
there are no force to counteract this, okay?
没有力量去抵消这件事，行吗？
So for example, the military.
比如说，军队。
The military will be for this because
军队会为此而行动。
they have shock and awe, and they are very confident they can win this war.
他们震惊又敬畏，且十分自信能赢得这场战争。
Okay? Iran itself wants this war
好的吗？伊朗本身也想要这场战争。
because it wants revenge
因为它想报仇。
against America. Okay?
对美国的行动。好的吗？
And then the President of the United States, will be Donald Trump,
随后美国总统将是唐纳德·特朗普，
he wants this war in order to cement his position
他想发动这场战争以巩固自己的地位。
as President. Okay? And so,
作为总统。好的吗？于是，
because of this, we can predict that
因为这样，我们可以预测
there'll be a war in Iran.
将会有一场伊朗战争。
Does that make sense? Okay.
那有道理吗？好。
Now, given this prediction,
现在，基于这个预测，
what we can then do is use mathematical modeling
接下来我们可以做的是使用数学建模
and statistics to turn this into an AI model.
并用统计数据把它变成一个AI模型。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好？这样有道理吗？
Okay? Now we have the AI model.
好？现在我们已经有了AI模型。
Now that we have the AI model,
现在我们已经有了AI模型，
what we need to do now is to refine it.
接下来我们需要做的是对它进行细化。
And the way we refined it is by going back in history
细化的方法是回溯历史。
and looking at every single war that started.
并且查看每一次战争的起始。
Does that make sense? And so,
这样有道理吗？于是，
you take this model and you look at the different wars.
你拿起这个模型，去查看不同的战争。
Okay? So for example, the 415 BCE war.
好的？比如说公元前415年的战争。
The invasion of Sicily by Athens.
雅典入侵西西里岛。
You look at 1941,
你看1941年。
Operation Barbarossa. Okay?
巴巴罗萨行动。好吗？
You have basically hundreds of wars that you can look at.
你基本上有数百场战争可以去研究。
And then you take this model and then you test it
然后你拿起这个模型，再去测试它。
using each of these wars.
使用这些战争中的每一场。
And what will happen is that
接下来会发生的事是……
the model will begin to refine itself.
模型会开始自我精炼。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这样说通吗？
So it becomes more and more refined.
于是它会越来越精细。
Okay? But then
好的？
that's one model for what causes war.
那是一个解释战争原因的模型。
I've also said that
我也说过，
Trump will become president.
特朗普将成为总统。
Right? Well
对吗？好吧
then, that's another model that you can use.
然后，这又是一个你可以使用的模型
And once you start putting all these models together,
一旦你开始把所有这些模型组合起来
what eventually happens is,
最终发生的事是，
what happens over time is you develop cycle history.
随着时间推移，你会形成循环历史。
Okay? Does this make sense, guys?
这样说清楚吗，大家？
All right? So now the question then is,
好的？那么现在的问题是，
okay, how would this AI model work?
好的，这个AI模型怎么运作？
Or what are the ideas behind this model?
或者这个模型背后的想法是什么？
Okay? So
好的？那么
we talk about game theory analysis a lot.
我们经常谈论博弈论分析。
All right? And the idea of game theory analysis is
好的？博弈论分析的意思是
that, okay, guys, there's really no good and evil.
那，好吧，大家，真的没有好与坏。
Okay? There are different players in a game.
好吧？游戏里有不同的玩家。
And they're all self -interested.
他们都是自利的。
They all want to win this game.
他们都想赢得这场游戏。
So they're going to develop strategies that
于是他们会制定策略，
optimize their ability to win this game.
以优化自己赢得这场游戏的能力。
Okay? So you can use game theory analysis.
好吧？那么你可以用博弈论来分析。
But then you can also use, you know, you can also develop new ideas
但随后你也可以用，你知道，你也可以提出新的想法。
that
那。
would help you better understand how the world works.
这将帮助你更好地理解世界运作方式。
So let's talk about some ideas
那么我们来聊聊本课程中出现的一些想法。
that have come up in this course.
这些想法已经在本课程中浮现。
All right? So
好的？那么
one thing I want to talk about is this week's European elections.
我想谈谈本周的欧洲选举。
Have you guys seen the news?
你们看过新闻了吗？
The elections to the European Parliament.
欧洲议会选举。
Right? And
好吧？而且
the results are pretty shocking.
结果相当震撼。
Because it signals a clear shift to the right.
因为它表明了向右的明显转变。
So, for example,
于是，例如，
Marylepain's party in France picked up a lot of votes.
玛丽勒潘在法国的党派获得了大量选票。
The AFD, the Alternative for Germany, the Alternative for Germany, which
德国之路，德国之路，德国之路，哪一支是德国的替代党，
is considered a right -wing organization,
它被认为是右派组织，
almost neo -Nazi, has picked up a lot of votes as well.
几乎是新纳粟，已获得大量选票。
The results were so dramatic
结果如此戏剧性
that Emmanuel Macron, the president of France,
埃马纽埃尔·马克龙，法国总统，
has called for an early election.
他已呼吁提前选举。
And it's possible in three months' time,
好的？三个月后，玛丽莱潘的党派将执政法国。
Marylepain's party will run and govern France.
好的？于是……
Okay? So
好的？
how do we explain this shift to the right?
我们怎么解释这一下右移？
And I want to explain three reasons.
我想解释三个原因。
Okay? The first reason is anti -immigration.
第一个原因是反移民。
Okay? So for the past 10,
好的？所以过去十年，二十年，欧洲从利比亚、叙利亚、伊拉克涌入了大量移民。
20 years, there have been a lot of immigrants to Europe from Libya,
from Syria, from Iraq,
好的？所以过去十年，二十年，欧洲从利比亚、叙利亚、伊拉克涌入了大量移民。
Afghanistan, Sudan, Somalia.
阿富汗、苏丹、索马里。
Okay? These are mainly non -immigrants.
好的吗？这些主要是非移民。
They are Muslim people who
他们是穆斯林人。
threaten the Christian social fabric of Europe.
威胁欧洲基督教社会结构。
And now Europeans are rebelling or revolting against that.
现在欧洲人对此起了反抗或起了革命。
Second thing that they don't like about Europe
第二件他们不喜欢的关于欧洲的事。
so far is the idea of federalism.
到目前为止是联邦主义的概念。
Okay? Or they can say bureaucratism.
好的吗？或者他们可以说官僚主义。
But this idea that a foreign power,
但这种概念是外部势力，
Brussels, mandates rules
布鲁塞尔，授权规则
that they must follow.
那他们必须遵循的事。
So they think it's very anti -democratic.
于是他们认为这很反民主。
Okay? And the third thing
好的吗？还有第三点
that
是
they're rebelling against is the idea of pan -Europeanism.
他们所反叛的，是泛欧洲主义的概念。
What the people of Europe are saying is,
欧洲人民所说的是，
there's no European identity, guys.
没有欧洲身份，大家。
There's a German identity, there's a French identity, Italian,
有德国身份，有法国身份，意大利身份，
Spanish, Portuguese, but there's no European identity.
西班牙语、葡萄牙语，但没有欧洲身份。
They're rebelling against the entire project of the EU.
他们正反叛欧盟的整个项目。
In fact, I would bet that
实际上，我打赌是
in about five years' time, the entire EU
大约五年后，整个欧盟
would be dead. Okay?
会死的。好吗？
Okay? Why are they opposed to
为什么他们反对？
pan -Europeanism?
泛欧主义？
Because, ultimately, they believe
因为，最终，他们认为
that it's about destroying local identity.
那是关于消灭地方身份的。
It's about destroying local community.
那是关于消灭地方社区的。
It's about destroying my relationship with my neighbors
关于破坏我与邻居的关系以及我的朋友和亲戚。
and my friends and my relatives.
Okay? And my family. Does that make sense?
好的？还有我的家人。这样说通吗？
Okay? It's imposing a foreign identity on me. And
好的？这就是把外来身份强加在我身上。
proponents of
主张者
the European Union would argue
欧盟会说
that, no, this is just a secular,
那，没错，这只是一个世俗的…
liberal idea.
自由主义理念。
Okay? The entire idea of the EU is
好吧？欧盟的整体理念是
that for hundreds of years, thousands of years,
那几百年、几千年，欧洲一直处于战争之中。为什么欧洲一直处于战争之中？
Europe has been at war. Why has Europe been at war?
Tribalism, right? Religion.
部落主义，对吧？宗教。
So the entire project of the EU is to get rid of
于是欧盟的整个项目就是摆脱……
this the factors that lead to war.
这就是导致战争的因素。
Local identity, nationalism,
地方身份，民族主义，
religion. Right?
宗教。对吧？
And what the European voters are saying to the EU is,
欧洲选民对欧盟说的是，
um, sorry,
嗯，抱歉，我们不想要世俗自由主义
we don't want secular liberalism because
we want to be human. Okay?
我们想成为人类。好吗？
What we strive for is not a abstract,
我们所追求的不是抽象，
liberal idea.
自由理念。
We strive for structure,
我们追求结构，
meaning, and purpose in our lives.
意义与目的。
Okay? What we really strive for is the capacity to love,
好的？我们真正追求的是爱、创作与学习的能力。
create, and learn.
好的？并且成长。
Okay? And grow.
Does that make sense? That's what we are fundamentally as human beings.
那有道理吗？这就是我们人类的根本。
And when you ask me
当你问我
to obey an abstract foreign entity
去服从一个抽象的外部实体
that is very far from me,
那离我很远，
then you are limiting or destroying the structure,
然后你就限制或破坏结构，
meaning, and purpose in my life.
意义与目的在我的生活中。
Okay? And so, that's what's going on,
好的？于是，事情就是这样，正在发生的事，
not just in Europe, but throughout the world.
不只是欧洲，而是全世界。
You think about Brexit, right?
你想想英国脱欧，对吧？
You think about the election of Donald Trump, right?
你想想唐纳德·特朗普的当选，对吧？
All these things have to do with this fundamental
所有这些事都与这个基本的
human urge to have structure, meaning,
人类有结构、意义的本能有关。
and purpose in our lives.
以及我们生活中的目的。
Okay? To have agency. Okay?
好吧？拥有主导性。好吧？
Does that make sense, guys? All right.
这样说通吗，大家？好的。
Any questions so far? Yeah?
还有问题吗？对吗？
Eric? Okay.
埃里克？好的。
So, Eric asked, okay,
于是，埃里克问，好的。
what is the source of all this?
什么是这一切的源头？
And what Dante and Homer
而且但丁与荷马会说什么？
would say is
会说什么？
the human heart, okay? The human heart.
人心，好的？人心。
This is just who we are.
这就是我们。
And if we cannot fulfill our human heart,
如果我们无法实现人心，
we will rebel.
我们会起义。
We will destroy.
我们会毁灭。
We will want to kill.
我们会想要杀人。
Okay? And so, in other words,
好的？那么，换句话说，
one idea in this AI model is
这个 AI 模型的一个想法是
that there is a fundamental
有一个根本的
underlying structure to human society.
基础结构属于人类社会。
Okay? If society conforms
好？如果社会符合人心结构，
to the structure of the human heart,
则……
this society will prosper.
这个社会将繁荣。
For example, Athens,
例如，雅典，
right? The ancient Greeks.
对吧？古希腊人。
That society prospered.
那社会繁荣了。
The word we used was eudaimonia, right?
我们用的词是eudaimonia，对吧？
Okay? But if society
好？但如果社会
represses the human heart, then
压抑人心，随后
ultimately the society will have to collapse at some point.
最终社会必将在某时崩溃。
Okay? So,
好？
that's another principle that we can use when developing this AI model.
那是我们在开发这个 AI 模型时可以使用的另一个原则。
The last idea that
最后一个想法是
we can use in developing this AI model is the idea of synchronicity.
我们在开发这个 AI 模型时可以使用的就是同步性。
Okay? Synchronicity. And
好？同步性。还有
the idea of synchronicity is, as a society,
同步性的概念是，作为一个社会，
how willing are people
人们愿意程度如何
how, how willing are people in following the rules?
人们遵守规则的愿意程度如何
It doesn't make sense. So, when you use the subway, do people actually follow traffic rules?
它有意义吗？那么，当你乘坐地铁时，人们真的会遵守交通规则吗？
When you use the subway, do people actually give up their seats for the elderly,
当你乘坐地铁时，人们真的会把座位让给老人吗？
for children, for pregnant women?
为孩子、为孕妇？
Okay? When you go to the park, do people actually pick up garbage
当你去公园时，人们真的会捡起垃圾吗？
and throw it in the garbage bin?
并把它扔进垃圾桶？
Okay? Synchronicity tells us that there's
好的？同步性告诉我们……
cohesion and trust in society, that society is resilient,
团结与信任，社会的韧性，社会的可持续发展，
okay? And that
好？以及那点
society is resilient because society can grow, okay, or learn from its mistakes.
社会韧性在于其能够成长，或者从错误中学习。
Okay? So, societies that are, that
好？所以，那些社会是，那些……
have high synchronicity will do better in the long term than societies with low synchronicity.
拥有高同步性的社会在长期表现上会优于低同步性的社会。
And so, societies with high synchronicity would include Japan
而且，高同步性的社会包括日本
and Germany, right?
以及德国，对吗？
And societies with low synchronicity would include
而低同步性的社会则包括
India and Brazil and China,
印度、巴西、中华，
okay? Does that make sense?
好？这样说对吗？
All right? So, when you go to the park, and
好的？所以，当你去公园时，
you're totally
你完全是
totally totally totally totally totally totally totally totally
完全完全完全完全完全完全完全完全
totally totally totally
完全完全完全
totally If you insert a human body into a human body,
完全如果你把一个人身体插进另一个人身体，那它为什么还是人身体？
then why would it be a human body?
请问？那它为什么还是人身体？
Excuse me? Why would it be a human body?
Okay, that's a great question. So
好的，这是个很好的问题。于是
one thing that
有一件事
was not supposed to happen
本来应该发生的
is the idea of mass society.
是大规模社会的概念。
Mass society. You can say that
大规模社会。你可以说它是……
mass society is a complete
大规模社会是完整的
deviation from
偏离人类历史。我们本来没有大规模社会。
human history. We're not supposed to have mass society.
而大规模社会完全是偶然的，历史的偶然。
And mass society is completely an accident, a historical accident.
And mass society is completely anaccident, a historical accident.
But when you have mass society, what happens is
但当你拥有大规模社会时，发生的事是……
that you need an elite.
你需要一个精英。
Okay? You need an elite.
好的？你需要一个精英。
But guess what, guys? The elite,
但你们猜怎么回事？精英，
the people in charge, they're not better than you and me. Okay? You understand?
掌权的人们不比你我好。好吗？你懂了吗？
We in this classroom could swap
我们在这教室里可以互换
for the leadership of the world, right?
为世界的领导者，对吧？
And guys, nothing would change.
而且，伙计们，什么也不会改变。
You understand? Right?
你明白了吗？对吧？
So you have mass society, and therefore you have to have an artifact of mass society.
于是你拥有大众社会，因此你必须拥有大众社会的象征。
And you have to have an elite. You have to have an elite. You have to have an elite. Because you need people in control.
你还得有精英。你得有精英。你得有精英。因为你需要掌权的人。
And because they're in control,
因为他们掌权，
they need to now maintain the illusion of their power.
他们现在需要保持自己权力的幻象。
Okay? They need to create fictions.
好吧？他们需要创造幻象。
For example, maybe, well,
举例来说，可能是……
I went to Yale or Harvard, and therefore I should be at the top.
我去过耶鲁或哈佛，所以我应该在顶端。
Or maybe I have a higher IQ than you do.
或者我智商比你高。
Or maybe, you know, my dad or my great -great -great -great -grandfather was king.
或者，你知道，我的爸爸或我的曾曾曾曾祖父是国王。
Okay? They had to create these fictions.
好吧？他们需要创造这些幻象。
Now, what happens over time is that
现在，随着时间的推移，发生的事是……
these fictions fall apart because
这些幻象最终会崩溃。
they're not that competent.
他们并不那么能干。
Okay? And the most recent example is you look at the global management of the economy,
好吧？最近的例子是你看看全球经济管理，
and you look at the global management of, like, COVID.
好吧？再看看全球管理，比如说COVID。
Okay? You look at the global management of war.
好吧？你看看全球战争管理。
Okay? They're pretty incompetent.
好吧？他们相当不熟练。
And so people sort of wake up and like, wait a minute.
于是人们会醒悟，稍等片刻。
These guys don't really know what they're doing.
这些人并不真正知道自己在做什么。
Okay? And now, so
好吧？现在，接着是……
now the elite is now forced to suppress us.
现在精英们被迫要压制我们。
Okay? That's a lie. They have to use force to make us obedient.
好吧？那是谎言。他们必须用武力让我们顺从。
Okay? And that's what's happening today.
好吧？这正是今天的情形。
And so this repression can go on for a long time,
于是这压制可以持续很久。
but to control us, they must repress the human heart.
但要控制我们，他们必须压制人心。
Okay? Because
好吧？因为
it's in the human heart to want to question,
它在人的心里想要提问
to be curious,
去好奇，
to grow.
去成长。
Okay? And if you think, like,
好吧？如果你想，像，
the people in charge don't know what they're doing, then
负责人们不知道自己在干什么，
you're sort of compelled to challenge them.
你会被迫去挑战他们。
And so what they have to do is suppress the human heart.
于是他们要做的就是压制人心。
And they do that by trying to get you to focus on buying new things.
他们通过让你专注于购买新东西来做到这一点。
But then you try and learn new things. But then you try and learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新东西。
But then you try and learn new things.
But then you try and learn new things. But then you try and learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新东西。然后你尝试并学到新东西。
But then you try and learn new things. But then you try and learn new things. But then you try and learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新东西。然后你尝试并学到新东西。然后你尝试并学到新东西。
But then you try and learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新东西。
But then you try and learn new things. But then you try and learn new things. But then
然后你尝试并学到新东西。然后你尝试并学到新东西。然后你尝试并学到新东西。
you try and learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新东西。
But then you try and learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新事物。
But then you try and
learn new things.
然后你尝试并学到新事物。
model okay you understand it has the human heart has to
模型好了，你明白它有人的心脏要变成像模型一样的脸部识别模型，好吗？
become like a model like facial recognition model okay does that make sense
好的，萨莉的问题是：不是这样吗？
okay so Sally's question is isn't it true
that we're all individual and unique
我们都是个体且独一
and isn't it true that
而且不是这样吗
over time we change okay and
随着时间我们会变化，好吗
that's that's great point but what Homer
那是个好点，但荷马会怎么说？
and Dante would say that
以及但丁会怎么说？
no no no no at the
不不不不……
fundamental level okay we all
基本层面，好吧，我们都
have the same desires we're motivated
有相同的愿望，我们被相同的需求驱动
by the same needs okay there's no one in this world
世界上没有人不去实现这三件事：爱、创作、成长
that does not want structure meaning and
那是个好点，但荷马会怎么说？
purpose now the way you want to achieve this may be different okay
以及但丁会怎么说？
but that's your underlying motivation and
不不不不……
there's no person in this world that
世界上没有人不去实现这三件事：爱、创作、成长
does not seek to have to achieve these three things like love create
有相同的愿望，我们被相同的需求驱动
and grow as people okay that's
世界上没有人不去实现这三件事：爱、创作、成长
when you achieve full happiness as a person when you feel
当你实现了完整的幸福感时，作为一个人，当你觉得自己与所爱之人结为连理并育有子女时
that you're married to someone you love you have children
当你从事一份富有创意的工作时
when you're doing a job that is creative and
when you're constantly learning every day and
当你每天不断学习、每天不断成长时，好的，当你实现了这三件事时，叫什么？
growing every day okay when you achieve that
these three things what do we call this when
当你每天不断学习、每天不断成长时，好的，当你实现了这三件事时，叫什么？
you've achieved all three things what do we
你已实现这三件事，我们称之为
call this eudaimonia right this is eudaimonia
这就是幸福感，确实是幸福感
this is what the Greeks meant by a happy
这正是古希腊所说的幸福
and self -fulfilled life it doesn't make sense okay
并且自我实现的生活，听起来不对劲，好吗？
so there may be
于是可能会有
differences in needs
需求上的差异
and motivation but
并且动机但
the fundamental at the fundamental level we're all human beings
在基本层面我们都是人类
and we're all driven by the same fundamental needs okay does
我们都由同样基本需求驱动，行吗？
that make sense okay okay
那就有道理了，好吗？
so Sally
于是萨莉
asked the question like how do you construct this
问了个问题：怎么构造它？
AI okay and so you're totally totally totally totally totally totally totally
AI好了，接着说，你完全完全完全完全完全完全完全
So for this AI to be valid,
所以要让这AI有效，
let me explain how we would actually implement.
让我来说明我们实际如何实现
So first of all,
首先，
you need at least 50 to 100 years to actually create this AI.
你至少需要50到100年才能真正创建这个AI。
And the reason why is that
原因是……
for this AI to be valid, you constantly need to be testing it.
为让这AI有效，你需要不断测试它。
So what I've been doing in this class is basically doing a self -AI,
所以我在这节课里基本上做了一个自我AI，
where I have an analytical model and I have a prediction.
我有一个分析模型和一个预测。
But guess what guys,
但你们猜怎么回事，
we won't know if my predictions
我们要等到现在起五十年后才能知道我的预测是否完全正确。
are fully correct until 50 years from now.
Is that correct? Therefore,
那是对的吗？因此，
I can't validate my analysis until 50 years from now.
我要等到现在起五十年后才能验证我的分析。
Does that make sense? And you need to be constantly doing this
那有道理吗？你还得不断做这件事。
where you have to be constantly making these predictions
你需要不断做这些预测
and seeing if they're correct or not.
并观察它们是否正确。
If they're not correct, what you have to do is go and
若不正确，你就得去
change these predictions
改这些预测
and analysis.
和分析。
Does that make sense? Then
那有道理吗？
what you have to do is you basically have to,
你需要做的事就是，你基本上要，
and this is actually what's the most time consuming, you have to rewrite history.
这实际上是最耗时的，你要重新写历史。
Do you understand? Because
你明白了吗？
most of the history is actually not correct.
大部分历史其实不正确。
So what you have to do is you have to take this AI model and
所以你要做的事就是，你要拿这个AI模型来，
look back at history and say,
回顾历史并说，
according to this AI model, what actually happened in the Peloponnesian War?
根据这个AI模型，伯罗奔尼撒战争到底发生了什么？
What actually happened in World War I? What actually happened during the Tang Dynasty? So
第一次世界大战到底发生了什么？唐朝期间又发生了什么？于是
you basically have to challenge the entire discipline of history
你基本上要挑战整个历史学科
and reconstruct a new history that
并重构一段新的历史，你认为更符合事实的基于此AI。
you think is more factually correct based on this AI.
于是你要一次完成这两件事。
So you have to be doing these two things at once.
So you have to be doingthese two things at once.
Making these predictions and seeing if you're correct, but
制作这些预测并检验其正确性，随后……
also going back throughout history
回溯历史全貌……
and seeing how history can be revamped or changed
观察历史如何被重塑或改写
so that it's more accurate.
使其更准确。
Does that make sense? That's a project,
这有道理吗？这就是一个项目，
but then there's the technology.
然后才有技术。
Because you actually need mathematicians and computer programmers and historians
因为你实际上需要数学家、电脑程序员和历史学家一起合作来构建这套 AI。
to collaborate together to build this AI.
于是我可以告诉你我会如何分析这个问题。
So I can tell you how I would analyze the issue,
So I can tell you how Iwould analyze the issue,
but then a mathematician has to turn this into a mathematical equation or a model.
但随后数学家必须把它转化为数学方程或模型。
Because computers only recognize data and numbers.
因为计算机只识别数据和数字。
They don't recognize ideas. I can't talk to a computer.
它们不识别概念。我无法与计算机对话。
I have to give a computer a number
我得给电脑一个数字
or an equation or a model for it to calculate on.
或者一个方程式或模型让它去算
Does that make sense?
这样说对吗
So it's not an easy project.
所以这不是一个简单的项目。
But the argument is that
但论点是，
if this project actually works,
如果这个项目真的能成功，
it would change the fate of humanity forever.
它将永远改变人类的命运。
Because if there's one thing that you notice in this class,
因为如果你在这门课里注意到一件事，
it's that we tend to repeat the same mistakes.
就是我们往往重复同样的错误。
The question is, why do we do that?
问题是，为什么我们会这么做？
It's because, the history that
因为我们掌握的历史完全是胡说八道。
we have is complete bullshit.
It just is. It's not true.
它就是这样。不是那样。
It can't be true. Okay?
它就不是那样。
There's things that we believe, which
有些我们相信的事物，若你想一想，肯定不对。
if you just think about it, can't be true.
Okay? And we did that like last semester when we talked about the rise of Christianity, right? You're telling me that
好的？我们像上学期那样讨论基督教的崛起时也是这么说的，对吧？你告诉我这位文盲叫耶稣的人能独自传播基督教。
this illiterate guy named Jesus was able to spread Christianity all by himself,
after he died? I don't believe that.
他死后呢？我不这么认为。
Okay? I think a much easier explanation is that
我想更简单的解释是……
it became co -opted by the Roman Empire in order to control the Empire.
它被罗马帝国合并，以控制帝国。
Right? But if you would talk to a historian,
对吧？但如果你去跟一位历史学家聊，
they would say, you're just wrong.
他们会说，你刚才说错了。
Okay? So, not only are you trying to predict the future,
好的？所以，你不仅在预测未来，
but you're trying to also correct the past, which is, I think, an even more difficult job.
但你也在尝试纠正过去，我想这更是个更难的工作。
Right? Any more questions?
对吧？还有问题吗？
Yeah, Eric?.
嗯，埃里克？
Excuse me? Oh, so, Eric asked a great question.
请问一下？哦，原来埃里克提了个好问题。
Will this cycle history model encounter edge cases?
这个循环历史模型会遇到边缘案例吗？
And the answer is, that's the best question, okay?
答案是：这才是最好的问题，好的？
That's a great question. And the answer is,
这是个好问题。答案是，
yes. What are edge cases?
是的。边缘案例是什么？
Do you guys know? What are edge cases in this model?
你们知道吗？这个模型中的边缘案例是什么？
. Who,
谁，
what would be edge cases here in history?
这里的边缘案例是什么？
Okay, it's called great man theory, okay?
好的，叫做伟人理论，好的？
Great man theory. And this is a problem.
伟人理论。这是一个问题。
Meaning, like, okay, we believe,
意思是，好吧，我们认为，
we argue that
我们主张
these underlying historical forces control humanity,
这些潜在的历史力量主宰人类
right? But now and then, you have this great man coming out of nowhere,
对吧？但时不时，你会出现一个从无名处出现的伟人，他永远改变人类历史的进程，好吗？
and he changes the course of human history forever, okay?
例子是，在我们有荷马之前，…
The example is, before we had Homer,
The example is,before we had Homer,
right? Then we had Dante.
对吧？然后我们有但丁。
Then we had Plato,
然后我们有柏拉图。
Jesus, Julius Caesar,
耶稣、朱利斯·凯撒。
Octavius, Poutin today, okay?
八月维乌斯，普丁今天，好吗？
We can't account for these people, because by definition,
我们无法解释这些人，因为按定义，
they're beyond, you know, beyond history.
他们已经超越，您知道，超越历史。
They can step outside of history and control history.
他们可以跳出历史并掌控历史。
That's what great men are. So how does your model account for that?
这就是伟人之所在。那你的模型如何解释呢？
Okay? And the answer is, you cannot.
好？答案是，你无法解释。
So, in foundation,
于是，在基础上，
okay, the solution, okay, but there is a solution to this.
好了，方案是，嗯，但确实有个方案。
The solution is to create another organization.
方案就是再创建一个组织。
Okay, remember that, technical history is an AI model.
好的，记住：技术历史是一个 AI 模型。
It's basically a computer. But
它基本上是台电脑。但
as Eric points out, you will always have edge cases.
正如埃里克指出的，你总会有边缘案例。
You'll always have someone appear out of nowhere.
你总会有人突然出现。
And for whatever reason,
不管什么原因，
he's able to manipulate events to control
他能操纵事件来掌控。
and direct history in his favor, okay?
并直接把历史倾向他，好吗？
So what you do to solve this problem is you create another organization,
为了解决这个问题，你就创建另一个组织，好吗？
okay? And in, I think, Asimov's foundation, it's called the Second Foundation.
我想在阿西莫夫的基础里，它叫第二基金会。
Okay? And the idea of the Second Foundation is
好的？第二基金会的想法是
that there is a computer, there is the AI, okay?
有一台电脑，有一个AI，好吗？
But behind the AI are a team of specialists
但AI背后是一支专家团队
who observe the AI, who observe history,
观察AI的人，观察历史的人，
and who correct the AI for edge cases, okay?
并且在边缘情况时修正AI的人，好吗？
Does that make sense? So if Putin appears and is like,
这样说通吗？如果普京出现并且是这样，
okay, well, clearly, I'm not accounting for Putin, well,
好的，显然，我没有把普京算进去，嗯，
then I change the equations in the AI to account for Putin, okay?
于是我在AI里改了方程，把普京算进去，嗯？
So this team of experts, the Second Foundation,
于是这支专家团队，第二基金会，
will correct the AI, right?
会修正AI，对吧？
Now, what's interesting about the Second Foundation is
现在，第二基金会有趣的地方是
that these people are telepaths.
这些人是通灵者。
Okay? Telepaths.
好的？通灵者。
Meaning that they can read your mind.
意思是他们能读懂你的心。
Not only can they read your mind, but they can troll your mind, okay?
不只是能读懂你的心，还能玩弄你的心，嗯？
So... And
于是……还有
that's another reason why I think we're really interested in something about psychohistory.
这又是我认为我们对心理历史感兴趣的另一个原因。
Like, okay, there's a promise that
比如说，嗯，有个承诺……
we can predict the future, but there's also a promise
我们可以预测未来，但也有一个承诺
that within our minds,
在我们的心中，
there are some special abilities that
有一些特殊能力
we might have the potential for, but
我们可能拥有潜力，但我们从未曾完全尝试实现。
we never ever fully attempted to achieve.
好的？这有道理吗？
Okay? Does that make sense?
And is it possible in the future
并且未来可否出现通灵者？
that telepaths will arrive I think yes.
我认为会出现。
And the answer is that you can make the argument that
答案是你可以这样论证。
these edge cases that Eric refers to, these great men of history,
这些边缘案例，埃里克提到的历史伟人，
they're actually telepaths.
他们实际上是通灵者。
Okay? Does that make sense? They're actually telepaths.
好的吗？这有道理吗？他们实际上是通灵者。
So someone like Putin, why is Putin able to do what he does?
那么像普京这样的人，为什么他能做到他所做的事？
And you can make the argument, like,
你可以这样论证，像是，
he has almost some telepathic abilities,
他几乎拥有某种通灵能力。
okay? He can read other people's minds.
好的？他能读懂别人的心思。
He can troll other people's minds.
他能把别人的心思玩弄。
How else can you explain that someone
还有什么办法解释这样的人呢？
who does not come
谁没来自特殊背景，对吧？
from a special background, right?
他不是俄罗斯精英之一。
He's not of the Russian elite.
He's not of theRussian elite.
But he's able to amass so much power
但他能在短短几十年内独自积聚如此多的力量
all by himself in only a few decades
只靠自己在仅仅几十年间就做到这一点
so that today, he's basically the emperor of Russia.
于是今天，他基本上就是俄罗斯的皇帝。
And all of Russia heeds his command.
俄国一切都听从他的指挥。
Russia just moves the way that he wants it to move.
俄国只按他所愿的方向运转。
Okay? So you can make the argument that
好？于是你可以这样论证。
Putin is almost a telepath.
普京几乎是个通灵者。
And is it possible
而且可能吗
that in the future we'll have more telepaths?
未来我们会有更多通灵者吗？
And we can, over time,
我们也可以，随着时间的推移，
harness the power of these telepaths
利用这些通灵者的力量
to create the second foundation and to control psychohistory?
来打造第二个基础并掌控心理史
Possibly, right? Okay?
可能吧？好吧？
Because, like, how else would we explain great men, okay?
因为，像，怎么解释伟人呢？
You look at someone like Homer and Dante, right?
你看像荷马和但丁的人，吧？
The only explanation that you can have for Homer and Dante is
对荷马和但丁的唯一解释是
they were... They had God -given gifts, okay?
他们是……他们拥有上帝赐予的天赋，好的？
Or maybe God was speaking to them.
或者上帝正对他们说话。
Or maybe they were just speaking for God.
或者他们只是为上帝发言。
Right? That's the only explanation that you can have for Homer
对吗？这就是你能给荷马的唯一解释。
and Dante because they so
以及但丁，因为他们如此
clearly stepped out of history and directed history.
清晰地从历史中跳出来并指引历史。
Okay, does that make sense? Okay?
好的，这有道理吗？好的？
But thanks for the question, Eric.
谢谢你的问题，埃里克。
Okay? So edge cases are great men
好的？边缘情况就是伟人
who appear now and then, and you cannot ever predict these people.
他们时不时出现，你永远预测不到这些人。
Okay? Any more questions?
好的？还有问题吗？
Okay. This...
好的。这个……
Yeah? Yes? Yes, Celine?
嗯？是吗？是的，塞琳？
..
……
Oh, that's a great question, okay?
哦，那是个很好的问题，好吗？
Um, okay. How do you model
嗯，好。你是怎么建模的
love, learn, and create, okay?
爱、学、创，好的？
And the answer is that
答案是这样：
there has to be a certain amount of
必须有一定量的
autonomy or agency
自主或能动性
in the lives of people.
在人的生活中。
Does that make sense? What we call freedom and liberty.
这样说通吗？我们所说的自由和自由度。
Because if you have freedom and liberty, then you're able to do what you want.
因为如果你拥有自由和自由度，你就能做你想做的事。
And what you want to do is love,
而你想做的就是爱，
um, create, and...
嗯，创造，和……
and grow, okay? Does that make sense?
然后成长，好吗？这通吗？
So you need to model, um, agency
所以你需要把主体性建模
and freedom into the structure, okay?
并把自由放进结构里，好吗？
The second thing is, um,
第二点是，嗯，
social interaction. Okay?
社会互动，好吗？
In other words, the more we're able to interact with each other,
换句话说，越能互相交流，
the more we're willing to love,
我们就越愿意去爱。
create, and grow.
创造，并成长。
Because these powers come from others, right?
因为这些力量来自他人，对吧？
You can't love yourself. You have to love someone else.
你不能自爱，你得去爱别人。
You can't create by yourself.
你自己做不到创造。
You have to create in a group, okay? And you can't learn by yourself.
你得在团队里做，行吗？你也不能单独学习。
You have to learn from others. Okay?
你得向别人学习，行吗？
So you also have to model in, um, as much group interaction as possible.
所以你也得尽量多做小组互动。
Okay? And the last thing is
好吧？最后一点是
you also have to model in the idea of compassion.
你还得把“同情”这个概念融进去。
Okay? So the idea here is that, um,
好的？所以这里的想法是，呃，
if I all put you on an island together,
如果我把你们全部放在同一座岛上，
okay, and you must survive,
好了，你们必须要生存下来。
well, you will become compassionate with each other,
好了，你们会彼此产生同情，
because that's the only way to survive, right?
因为那是唯一能生存下去的办法，对吧？
But, if I put you guys into a bank,
不过，如果我把你们放进银行，
and I say to you that
我跟你们说，如果你们赚了一百万，我再给你们两百万，谁赚得最多，我就送一辆法拉利，猜猜谁？
if you make a million dollars, and I give you two million dollars,
whoever makes the most money, I will give a Ferrari to, guess what, guys?
我跟你们说，如果你们赚了一百万，我再给你们两百万，谁赚得最多，我就送一辆法拉利，猜猜谁？
You will all hate each other.
你们会互相仇恨。
You will all want to kill each other, okay?
你们会互相想杀了，行吗？
You understand? So
你明白了吗？
this model also has to factor in compassion.
这个模型还要考虑同情。
How compassionate is this society?
这个社会有多同情？
Okay? Because if you have compassion,
好吧？因为有同情的话，
then people are willing to work together.
然后人们愿意一起工作。
If people are willing to work together, then people will have the greater capacity to love, create, and grow.
如果人们愿意一起工作，那么他们就会有更大的能力去爱、创造和成长。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好吧？这样说通吗？
Actually, guys, we have all these theories.
实际上，伙计们，我们有这么多理论。
It's just like no one's turned this into a mathematical model,
就像没有人把它们变成社会的数学模型一样，
okay, for society. Any more questions?
好了，接着说。
Yeah? .
嗯？
Yeah, so
嗯，好吧
Eric asked a question,
埃里克提了个问题
is it possible to
它可否完全理解人类行为与动机？
completely understand human behavior and motivation?
还有两种不同的方式来观察这个问题，行吗？
And there are two different ways of looking at the issue, okay?
The first way is to use a social science approach,
第一种方法是采用社会科学的视角，
okay? So you look at economics, psychology,
好吧？于是你会去研究经济学、心理学，
anthropology, sociology, right?
人类学、社会学，对吧？
What are they trying to do?
他们在做什么？
They're trying to figure out mathematically
他们正试图用数学方法弄清楚是什么驱动我们，行吗？
what drives us, okay?
You understand?
你明白了吗？
But there's another approach.
但还有另一种方法。
It's called the literature approach,
它叫做文学方法。
which is that we can't actually quantify
这就是我们无法真正量化的原因
or explain human behavior, okay?
或者解释人类行为，行吗？
But there are truths that can be expressed in literature.
但有些真理可以用文学来表达。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这样说通吗？
So think about the very first book we read, The Iliad.
那么想想我们刚读的第一本书，伊利亚德。
Right? Where
对吧？
Achilles has killed Hector and Prime wants the body back.
阿基琉斯杀死赫克托尔，普莱姆想取回尸体。
So Prime sneaks into Achilles' tent and kisses his hand,
于是普莱姆潜入阿基琉斯帐篷，吻了他的手，右吗？
right? That moment.
那一刻。
You can never mathematically express it.
可以用数学表达不了。
You can only write about it.
只能写出来。
But think about how much truth and power
但想想其中蕴含的真理与力量。
is in that one scene.
在那一幕里。
Okay? Does that make sense, Eric?
好吧？这样说通吗，埃里克？
Okay? So again, I think someone like Homer
好吧？所以，我想像荷马那样的人会是这样。
and Dante,
而且但丁，
their mission is to express to us,
他们的使命是向我们表达，
in the most beautiful way, the human truths, okay?
以最美的方式，呈现人类真理，好吗？
Like what drives us.
像推动我们的那样。
And Dante is very explicit.
而但丁则非常明确。
He says that what drives us is love
他说推动我们的就是爱。
and the willingness to imagine, okay?
并且愿意去想象，好的？
That's who we are. If we love, we'll be more human.
这就是我们。若我们爱，我们更有人性。
If we imagine, we'll be more human, okay?
若我们想象，我们更有人性，好的？
And that's really the argument I make as well.
而这正是我所提出的论点。
All right? And that
好了？而且这点是……】
has to be the underlying truth
】
of whatever AI model you create, okay?
无论你创建的AI模型是什么，好的？
All right? Any more questions? Yeah?
好了？还有问题吗？嗯？
Okay. Okay.
好的。好的。
So, Celine asked a great question.
于是，塞琳提出了一个很好的问题。
Okay, well, if it says that
好的，嗯，如果它说我们想要爱、创造和成长，那为什么我们最终会自我毁灭？
we want to love, create, and grow, then why do we end up destroying ourselves?
we want to love, create, and grow, thenwhy do we end up destroying ourselves?
And the answer is that love
而答案是，爱与恨是一股力量。
and hate are one force.
你明白吗？如果我不能爱你，我就会恨你。
You understand? If I can't love you, I'm going to hate you.
You understand, okay? Guess what, guys?
你明白吗，好吗？猜猜，大家？
Creation and destruction are two different things. Destruction is one force as well.
创造与毁灭是两件事。毁灭也是一种力量。
If I can't create, then I want to destroy
如果我不能创造，那我就想毁灭。
because my need for creation can't be satisfied.
因为我的创造需求未能得到满足。
Does that make sense? So, a society
这样说有道理吗？于是，一个社会
that nurtures our willingness to love
培养我们愿意去爱的意愿。
and create and grow, like the Greeks,
并且创造并成长，像古希腊人一样，
will flourish, okay?
将会繁荣，好吗？
But eventually, you reach a point where
但最终，你会到达一个点
the elite have amassed power.
精英已聚集力量。
They've centralized and consolidated power, and so
他们已集中并巩固力量，随后……
they want to turn everyone
于是他们想让所有人……
else into basically a slave.
变成基本的奴隶。
When you're a slave, you can't love.
当你是奴隶时，你就不能爱。
You can't create. You can't learn.
你不能创造，也不能学习。
You can't grow. Therefore, you rebel, and you destroy the society.
你无法成长。因此，你会反叛，并摧毁社会。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
好的？这样说通吗？好的？
But, again, the fundamental human need are these three things,
但，再次说，人的基本需求是这三件事，
but within each of these things is another force.
但在这些事物之中又有另一股力量。
And if love can't express itself, then hate will express itself.
如果爱无法表达，恰好恨便会表达。
Does that make sense? Okay?
这样说通吗？好的？
All right. Any more questions?
好的。还有问题吗？
Yeah?.
嗯？
... .
……
. So, Sally asked a great question, which is, like, who
. 所以，萨莉问了一个很好的问题，就是，呃，谁
would control this AI?
会控制这台 AI 吗？
And how can we ensure that
那我们怎么确保呢？
this AI is not exploited by the
这台 AI 不是被……
elite in order to justify their corruption and cruelty, okay?
精英们用来证明他们的腐败与残暴，行吗？
And the answer has to be
而答案必须是
really the second foundation, okay?
真正是第二个基石，行吗？
Basically, a group of scholars,
基本上，一群学者，
academics, experts, who
学者、专家、专业人士，
dedicate themselves to this AI, okay?
致力于这台 AI，行吗？
And this AI, the other thing is that it has to be open and transparent.
这台 AI，另一件事是它必须开放透明。
That's why it's so hard to build, right?
这就是它构建之难的原因，行吗？
It has to be open and transparent.
它必须开放透明。
Okay? If it's open and transparent, then
好的？如果它是开放透明的，大家就得同意这台 AI 将用于好事，行吗？
everyone has to agree that this AI is going to be used for good, okay?
Meaning that what this AI does is you can ask it different questions,
意思是这台 AI 的工作是你可以问它不同的问题，
and it will give you different scenarios.
它会给你不同的情景。
And we can all agree on which scenario we want,
我们可以一起决定想要哪一个情景。
and therefore we can agree on what action to take, okay?
于是我们就能就采取什么行动达成一致，行吗？
So this AI has to be part of a democratic system
所以这台 AI 必须成为民主体系的一部分
where everyone is involved.
其中每个人都参与其中
Otherwise, as Sally points out,
否则，正如萨莉所指出的，
it can only be abused,
它只能被滥用，
okay? It can only be used to oppress others,
好吗？它只能用来压迫别人。
okay?
好吗？
But the point of this AI is that
但这台 AI 的要点是
it gives us a platform
它给我们一个平台
as humans to agree on certain actions
作为人类，我们需要就某些行动达成共识
that we must stick together, okay?
我们必须团结一致，好吗？
Does that make sense? So for example, we can all agree
这样说通吗？举个例子，我们都能同意
that climate change is bad.
气候变化是坏事。
We can all agree that war is bad, right?
我们都能同意战争是坏事。
But this AI will actually give us solutions to these problems
这台 AI 实际上会给我们这些问题的解决方案。
because this AI can map out the future for us.
因为这台 AI 能为我们绘制未来。
And AI will say, well, listen,
而 AI 会说，好吧，听着，
if the United States intervenes in Ukraine,
如果美国介入乌克兰，
then this will happen, right?
然后这件事就会发生，没错吗？
The United States attacks Iran, then this will happen.
美国攻击伊朗后，这件事就会发生。
And that becomes a very powerful argument for correct
于是这就成为了一个很有力的论据。
and proper behavior, okay?
并且正确的行为，好的？
Does that make sense? All right.
这样说通吗？全部好。
But again, guys,
但再说一次，伙计们。
this is just conjecture, okay?
这只是推测，好的？
And I've already said this.
我已经说过了。
It's going to take at least 50 to 100 years to build this AI,
要建成这个AI至少要50到100年。
and you will be up against tremendous opposition,
并且你将面临巨大的对抗，好的？史学家们会喜欢这件事的。
right? Historians aren't going to like this.
精英们会喜欢这件事的，好的？】
The elite aren't going to like this, right?
}
But at the same time, we have to remember, like, guess what?
但与此同时，我们要记住，呃，猜怎么说？
Homer, I'm pretty sure if Homer
荷马，我很确定如果荷马
were living in a centralized society,
居住在一个集中的社会里，
the elite would be opposed to him, okay?
精英们会对他有反对，好的？
Because he was making fun of very famous Greeks,
因为他在嘲笑非常著名的希腊人，好的？
like Achilles and Menelaus and Agamemnon, right?
比如阿基里斯、梅涅拉俄斯和阿伽门农，好的？
He was making fun of these guys. Well, guess what?
他在嘲笑这些人。好了，猜怎么说？
When Homer's writing, society had collapsed, right?
当荷马写作时，社会已经崩溃，没错吧？
When Dante was writing, society had collapsed.
当但丁写作时，社会已经崩溃。
So if it is true, if my predictions are correct
如果这是真的，如果我的预测正确
and society is approaching collapse,
社会正接近崩溃
then there should be a lot of space and leeway
那就会有很多空间和余地
and flexibility to create this AI, okay?
并且有灵活性来创造这AI，好吗？
Okay. Any more questions?
好的。还有别的问题吗？
Yeah?.
是吗？
That's a great question.
这是个很好的问题。
So won't different people, different nations want different outcomes?
所以不同的人、不同的国家会想要不同的结果吗？
And the answer is yeah. Like, if you are alive today,
答案是的。比如说，如果你今天还活着，
if you're America, you want America to be a hegemon.
如果你是美国人，你想让美国成为霸权。
If you're Putin, you want Russia to be the hegemon.
如果你是普京，你想让俄罗斯成为霸权。
If you're China, you want China to be the hegemon, right?
如果你是中国人，你想让中国成为霸权，对吗？
You want different outcomes. So
你想要不同的结果。所以
my argument is that
我的论点是
the structure of society today is not sustainable.
今天社会的结构不再可持续。
Everything's going to collapse. And
一切都将崩溃。然后
we are going to transition from a
我们将从约八十亿人过渡到一十亿人。
population of about 8 billion people to a population of 1 billion people.
population of about 8 billion peopleto a population of 1 billion people.
And when you have 1 billion people and,
当你拥有一亿人口时，
like, there's no place to grow crops,
比如说，没有地方种植被子，
and pollution is everywhere,
而且污染无处不在。
and war is everywhere, guess what happens?
战争无处不在，猜猜会怎样？
Humans are united in their goals,
人类在目标上已统一，
which is basically how do we create a better civilization,
这基本就是我们如何创造更好文明的方式。
okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这样说通吗？
When all of a sudden it's collapsed, everyone's like, how do we recreate civilization?
突然间全局崩溃，大家都在问：我们怎样重建文明？
That's the goal. But in a more progressive, more democratic,
这就是目标。但要更进步、更民主的方式。
and more prosperous way.
更繁荣的方式。
Okay? That's what I'm betting on.
好的？这就是我下注的。
But I don't know, okay? And again,
但我不知道，好的？再说一次，
if everyone's fighting over the AI, this AI cannot be created, okay?
如果大家都在争夺这AI，它就无法被创造，好吗？
Because different people will want this AI to be biased in a different way.
因为不同的人会想让这AI偏向各自的立场。
This AI can only work if it steps outside of history
这AI只有在脱离历史后才能运作。
and steps outside of human interests, okay?
并且脱离人类利益，好吗？
If it's speaking for all of humanity rather than one nation or one group of people.
它若能代表全人类而非单一民族或单一群体发声。
Okay? Any more questions?
好？还有别问吗？
Is this clear to you guys?
这对你们来说清楚吗？
Alright. So, um...
好的。那么，嗯……
Alright. So, this is the very end,
好的。那么，这就是最后了。
and I'll spend, like, five more minutes to talk about
我会再花大约五分钟来聊聊今年，好吗？
this year, okay?
好吧，嗯……
So, um...
This is the very first time I've taught both courses, okay?
这可是我第一次同时教授这两门课程，明白吗？
In the first semester, we read the great books.
在第一学期，我们阅读了这些经典书籍。
And... Um...
然后……嗯……
I was blown away
我被你们的热情所震撼
by how much you guys enjoyed the great books. And
我被你们对这些经典书籍的喜爱所震撼。并且
how much you benefit from reading the great books,
你们通过阅读这些经典书籍获得的收益
okay? And quite honestly, I don't think anyone has tried this before.
好的？说实话，我觉得之前没人尝试过。
Um... I know there are great books courses in university,
嗯……我知道大学里有经典书籍课程，
but not at the pace
但节奏不一样。
that we had,
我们曾经得过的那样，
and certainly not at the level of difficulty that we had, okay?
而且肯定不如我们之前的难度，好的？
So you guys should be proud of yourself, because the great books courses was very hard.
所以你们应该为自己感到自豪，因为经典书籍课程非常艰难。
And, um... You enjoyed it.
嗯……你们玩得很开心。
Um... Even today, most of you really like the Iliad, right?
嗯……今天你们大多数人还是很喜欢《伊利亚特》吧？
You guys still remember the Iliad and think very highly of it, okay?
你们还记得《伊利亚特》，并且评价很高，对吧？
Um... So, so...
嗯……所以，嗯……
So that's very impressive, so thank you.
所以这很令人印象，感谢你。
This semester is also a new course, where
本学期也是一门新课程，
we looked at geopolitics.
我们看了地缘政治。
And, um... I'm...
嗯……我……
I'm also very impressed
我也很印象。
by how much you've grown as well
你们成长了多少，已在这门课中。嗯……
in this course. Um...
你们的思考方式更为逻辑。
The way you guys think, it's much more logical.
The way you guys think,it's much more logical.
Much more analytical.
更具分析性。
You guys are asking great questions, okay?
你们提出了很好的问题，行吗？
So, um...
嗯……
Thank you again, because...
再次感谢你们，因为……
You don't have to work hard in this course, but you chose to work hard.
你们在这门课里不必费劲，但你们选择了努力。
And this is gonna carry you very far, um...
这将把你们带得很远，嗯……
in life, okay?
在生活里，行吗？
So, um...
所以，嗯……
The course is...
这门课是……
Um... Has come to an end.
嗯……已经结束。
And I will share with you
我会与大家分享
um... Why I teach this course, okay?
嗯……我为什么开这门课，行吗？
Because... Some of you know,
因为……你们中有些人知道，
I do have a very prestigious education background,
我确实拥有非常有名望的教育背景，
as well as a career background,
以及职业背景。
okay? And...
好吧？然后……
I could have been, what, a lawyer, I think?
我本来可以是个律师，应该是吧？
A lawyer. A rich lawyer.
一个律师。一个富有的律师。
A professor, okay?
一名教授，行吗？
But instead, I'm teaching high school in China.
但我在中国教高中。
Right? Why am I doing this?
对吗？我为什么要这么做？
It's because... Um...
因为……呃……
I have three kids.
我有三个孩子。
Okay? I have three young kids.
好的？我有三个小孩子。
My eldest is six.
我的大儿子六岁。
My youngest is only about eight months.
我的小儿子才八个月。
Okay? And as a father,
我作为父亲，
you have to believe in a better world.
你要相信更好的世界。
But not only do you have to believe in a better world, you have to imagine.
但你不仅要相信更好的世界，还要去想象。
You have to fight for it.
你要为之而战。
Because... Um...
因为……呃……
You have to leave behind a legacy for your children.
你要为孩子们留下遗产。
Okay? So,
好的？所以，
why I teach this course is to bring you a message of hope.
我开这门课的原因是给你们送去一份希望的讯息。
Okay? Like, through your own imagination,
好吧？就是通过自己的想象，
through your own hard work, you can create a better world.
通过自己的努力，你们就能创造更好的世界。
You don't have to sit back and just let the world happen.
你不必坐着等着世界发生。
You don't have to wait for the future.
你不必等待未来。
You can make it happen. And...
你可以让它发生。并且……
If you really...
如果你真的……
work hard at it, you can make the world a better place.
努力去做，你就能让世界变得更好。
And I think, like, this year
我想，这一年……
has proven to me
已向我证明
that I can make the world a better place
我可以让世界变得更好
if I work hard. Because I've seen the growth in all of you.
只要我努力
Okay? So, I hope we can stay in touch.
好的？所以，我希望我们能保持联系。
I hope that...
我希望……
Um... You will tell me how you progress, because
嗯……你会告诉我你的进展。
I'm very confident that all of you will do very well in university.
我很有信心，你们在大学里会表现得很出色。
And in life. And maybe at some point,
在生活中也是如此。也许在某个时刻，
we can share this dream of psychohistory.
我们可以共享这份关于心理史的梦想。
You know? I know it sounds very complicated.
你知道吗？我知道听起来很复杂。
It's very abstract. But
很抽象。但
to make this work, you need a lot of people working together.
要把这件事做成，得有很多人一起合作。
Okay? And it's something that's not going to happen tomorrow.
好的？这件事不是明天就能完成的。
But it's something that we might come back to later on in our lives.
但它是我们以后生活中可能会再次回到的事。
Okay? So, that's it.
好的？好了，就是这样。
Thank you. And we'll stay in touch.
谢谢。我们会保持联系。
Okay? Subtitles by the Amara.org community
好的？字幕由Amara.org社区制作。